Guide to the Time Inc. Atlantic Recording Company and Elektra Entertainment Records 1964-1993 (bulk, 1974-1993) MS 3009-RG 51
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Atlantic Recording Company and Elektra Entertainment Records
1964-1993 (bulk, 1974-1993)
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 51
4 Linear feet in 4 record cartons
Atlantic Recording Corporation and Elektra Entertainment are music record labels owned by Warner Communications at the time of its merger with Time Inc. The labels were then managed under the Time Warner Entertainment division. The collection contains print-outs of sales data for artists signed with both labels.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Open to qualified researchers with the exception of restricted materials. Restricted materials include contracts and are located in box R86.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically based on the original arrangement.
Historical Note
Atlantic Recording Corporation (usually known as Atlantic Records) was a record label founded by Ahmet Ertegun and Herb Abramson in 1947 which became known for specializing in the jazz, R&B, and soul genres. In 1967, Atlantic Records was purchased by Warner Brothers. Warner Brothers went through a series of mergers or sales to become Kinney National Services.
Elektra Entertainment was a record label founded by by Jac Holzman and Paul Rickolt in 1950 which became known for releases in the rock and contemporary folk genres. Elektra was purchased in 1970 by Kinney National Services in 1970 which changed its name to Warner Communications in 1972.
In 1990 Warner Communications merged with Time Inc. to form Time Warner. In 1993 Time Warner Entertainment was formed as a division of the company which included music labels such as Atlantic Records and Elektra Entertainment.
Citations:
Edwards, David, and Mike Callahan. "The Atlantic Records Story." Both Sides Now Stereo Newsletter, Both Sides Now Publications, February 20, 2000, www.bsnpubs.com/atlantic/atlanticstory.html.
Sutel, Seth. "Warner Music Slashes Jobs, Ousts Bigwigs". The Washington Post (AP), March 2, 2004, https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A22519-2004Mar2.html?sections=http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/business.
Provenance
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Related Materials
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the Time Inc. Records. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the Time Inc. Records (MS 3009). The Henry Luce Papers (MS 3014) were acquired with the Time Inc. Records. The collection of books acquired with the records are cataloged as the Time Inc. Reference Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of data print-outs listing artists signed with Atlantic Records and Elektra Entertainment with sales figures for releases for certain periods of time as well as a binder of information on the gathering of this matertial.
Corporation records; Corporations -- History; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Music publishing; Music trade; Organization files; Popular music -- United States.; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Time, inc. -- Archives; Time, inc. -- History
- Agent's Label Copies Test Sample Atlantic, 1968-1974 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 1-2)
- Agent's Label Copies Test Sample Elektra Records, 1972-1974 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 3)
- Artists C-D, 1967-1975 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 4-6)
- Artists N-R, 1969-1985 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 7-8)
- Artists S, 1964-1983 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 9-10)
- Artists T-Z, 1966-1984 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 11-12)
- Atlantic Contract [Restricted], 1968 (Offsite-box R86, Folder 91)
- Atlantic Final Artist Spread Report – All Units, 1987 (Offsite-box 4085, Folder 13-14)
- Atlantic Final Artist Spread Report – All Units, 1988 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 1-2)
- Atlantic Final Artist Spread Report – All Units, 1989 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 3-4)
- Atlantic Final Artist Spread Report – Reg Units 1990 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 5-7)
- Atlantic Final Artist Spread Report – Reg Units 1990 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 8)
- Atlantic Royalty Analysis 1974 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 9)
- Atlantic Royalty Analysis 1975 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 10)
- Atlantic Royalty Analysis 1976 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 11)
- Atlantic Royalty Analysis 1977 (Offsite-box 4086, Folder 12)
- Atlantic Sales 1969-1971 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 1-2)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1978 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 3)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1979 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 4)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1980 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 5)
- Atlantic Spread Report 198, 1981 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 6)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1982 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 7-8)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1983 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 9)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1983 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 10-11)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1984 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 12)
- Atlantic Spread Report 1985 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 13)
- Atlantic Spread Report, 1987 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 14)
- Atlantic Track Listings, 1972, 1975, 1990 (Offsite-box 4087, Folder 15)
- Elektra 1972-1974 Releases Sales 1973-1991, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 1)
- Elektra Entertainment Foreign History Analysis Report, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 2)
- Elektra Entertainment National Catalog Sales by Record Project, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 3)
- Elektra National Catalog Sales Dollars Report, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 4)
- Elektra Records Database Releases Domestic Sales 1983-1992/Foreign Sales 1987-1992 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 5)
- Elektra Release Listing 1972-1974 Domestic Sales 1976, 1992 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 6)
- Elektra Release Listing 1972-1974 Domestic Sales 1977, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 7)
- Elektra Release Listing 1972-1974 Sales, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 8-10)
- Elektra Research, 1992 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 11)
- Elektra Sales, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 12)
- Elektra "Best of" Releases Domestic Sales 1983-1992 and Foreign Sales 1987-1992, 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 13)
- Warner Records Binder #1 (Walter J. Grabowski), 1993 (Offsite-box 4088, Folder 14-16)